NICHOLAS SPYRISON

DATA SCIENTIST

Professional Summary

I am a published data scientist with extensive experience with a wide variety of multivariate data. I am client-focused, results-orientated with a passion for using data visualization, complex analysis, and factor analysis to simplify complicated problems into interpretable takeaways.

SKILLS

Strengths	Data vis, dimension reduction, feature engineering, machine learning & interpretability
Programs	R, Python, Git & GitHub, Excel & VBA, LATEX
Packages	ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, DALEX, keras, pandas, scikit-learn
Models	xgboost, neural networks, random forest, SVM, logistic, K-NN, K-means, parameter tuning
REPORTING	R markdown, Shiny, SSRS, Tableau, PowerBL WebFOCUS, Crystal

SOFTWARE (R PACKAGES)

SPINIFEX	Facilitates the manual tour. Provides an interface for composing animated and interactive		
	linear projections to various formats.	$\underline{\mathtt{Link}}$	
CHEEM	Given a nonlinear model, find the local explanation of each observation. Provides an interact		
	coordinated views in a shiny application. Novel analysis and visuals to explore	the local	
	explanations with the manual tour. This general analysis is demonstrated on SHA	AP values	
	from random forest models.	Link	

EDUCATION

Degree	Ph.D., Information Technology/Stats	under examination, 2018 — Now
University	Monash University	Melbourne, Australia
Focus	Dimension reduction, interactive and dynamic data visualization, machine learning models	
THESIS	Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-din	nensional data <u>Link</u>
Degree	B.Sc, Statistics , Physics & Mathematics minors	2008 — 2012
University	Iowa State University	Ames, Iowa

Work Experience

Job Title	Data Fluency Instructor	2018 — Now
Employer	Monash University	Melbourne, Australia
Programs	R. Git. PowerBI. Rest API	

Data Fluency Instructor: Lead various workshops (10-30 attendees) on R, modeling, programming, PowerBI, and Git. Teaching Assistant: Postgraduate data exploration and visualization & business and economic statistics. Research Officer: Criminology & human geology data cleaning, analysis & reporting.

JOB TITLE Business Intelligence Developer

EMPLOYER CPI Card Group

PROGRAMS SQL, SSRS, Crystal, Oracle BICS, Excel

Develop mid- and high-abstraction database queries. Database reporting; across 4 reporting platforms. Developed supply chain report tracking a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD.

JOB TITLEBusiness Intelligence Developer2015 — 2016EMPLOYERUDR Real Estate Investment TrustDenver, CO

PROGRAMS SQL, SSRS, OLAP/MOLAP, WebFOCUS

Query, analysis, & reporting. Responsible for transitioning reports from WebFOCUS reporting to SSRS. On-call for enterprise-wide ETL process.

JOB TITLE Business Intelligence Analyst 2014 — 2015
EMPLOYER Heartland Financial USA Dubuque, IA
PROGRAMS SQL, WebFOCUS

Database querying, data analysis, and enterprise reporting.

JOB TITLE Delivery Data Analyst

EMPLOYER IBM — International Business Machines

Dubuque, IA

Programs R, Excel, VBA

Statistical variance analysis & metric reporting to teams and management. IBM's lean/six sigma methodology, root cause analysis, ETL scripting via VBA macros for 0.5 FTE savings across the team. Step-wise model selection predicting service time.

JOB TITLEVarious seasonal employment2010 — 2012EMPLOYERIowa State University & Ames LaboratoryAmes, IA

Laboratory Technician: Superconductivity instrumental measurement and data analysis. *Physics Tutor*: Instructed Classical Physics to groups of 5 students.

Honors and awards

Monash Postgraduate publication Award 2022 Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights Category — 1st place Link — 2020 ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award 2018 UseR2018 Datathon — 3rd place 2018 Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship 2018 - 2022 Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship 2018 - 2022 Nominated for Student Employee of the Year 2011 & 2012 American Legion Award 2008

MEMBERSHIP & ENGAGEMENT

Australian Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers (ACEMS) Statistical Society of Australia (SSA), Victorian Branch American Statistical Association, District 4

REFERENCES

Professor Di Cook, PhD supervisor Email: dicook@monash.edu, Office: +61 (0)3 9905 2608 Professor Kim Marriott, PhD supervisor Email: kim.marriott@monash.edu, Office: +61 (0)3 9905 5525

DOCTORAL THESIS

[1] Nicholas S Spyrison. "Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. PhD thesis. Monash University, Mar. 2022. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/thesis_ns/blob/master/docs/thesis_ns.pdf.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- [2] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. "spinifex: an R Package for Creating a Manual Tour of Low-dimensional Projections of Multivariate Data". en. In: *The R Journal* 12.1 (2020), p. 243. ISSN: 2073-4859. DOI: 10.32614/RJ-2020-027. URL: https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2020/RJ-2020-027/index.html (visited on 10/16/2020).
- [3] Stuart Lee et al. "The state-of-the-art on tours for dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. In: WIREs Computational Statistics (Dec. 2021), p. 21. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: 10.1002/wics.1573. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/wics.1573 (visited on 12/10/2021).

SOFTWARE (R PACKAGES)

- [4] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. spinifex: Manual Tours, Manual Control of Dynamic Projections of Numeric Multivariate Data. 2021. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spinifex.
- [5] Nicholas Spyrison. cheem: Interactively Explore the Support of Local Explanations of a Model. 2022. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cheem.

Conference proceedings

- [6] Nicholas S. Spyrison. "spinifex: visualizing local structure of higher dimensions". en. In: Brisbane, Australia, 2018. URL: https://user2018.r-project.org/poster/(visited on 07/28/2020).
- [7] Madeleine Barrow, Jieyang Chong, and Nicholas Spyrison. "Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions". en. In: *Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category*. Oct. 2020, p. 4. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/melb_datathon2020/blob/master/_paper/paper.pdf (visited on 02/09/2022).
- [8] Nicholas Spyrison, Benjamin Lee, and Lonni Besançon. "Is IEEE VIS *that* good?" On key factors in the initial assessment of manuscript and venue quality". In: *IEEE AltVis Workshop*. type: article. July 2021. DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/65wm7. URL: https://osf.io/65wm7/ (visited on 08/21/2021).